茶道中人曾语 茶壶经过多道茶的浸润
The great artisans say the more the teapot is used.
将愈加温润如玉 焕然有光
the more beautiful it becomes.
养壶在于重复多次地用老茶汤汁浇壶身
The pot is seasoned by repeatedly pouring tea over the surface.
陶土吸入茶汤的沉淀
The deposit left on the clay.
形成深厚温润的表面光泽
creates this beautiful patina over time.
有些茶壶焕发的典雅的幽光
Some pots, the clay has been burnished.
是经四百年前的茶汤浸润而成
by tea made over 400 years ago.
博物馆将在十分钟后关门
This museum will be closing in 10 minutes.
四百年的古董 他们允许你用来泡茶喝呢
400 years old, they're letting you use it to make yourself a brew.
有些东西注定不该空坐在玻璃护罩里
Some things aren't supposed to sit behind glass,
它们生来就该被人触碰
they're made to be touched.
为人所用
To be handled.
这些茶壶需要关爱
These pots need attention.
陶土有裂纹了
The clay is cracking.
我不觉得浇一丁点儿茶汁 会有多大帮助
Well, I can't see how a tiny splash of tea is going to help.
有时候一些东西需要你仔细地观察
Sometimes you have to look hard at something.
才能品味其价值
to see its value.
看到么
See?
这一只的光泽稍微亮些
This one shines a little brighter.
不知道…
I don't suppose…
我是说…
Um, I mean…
你愿意跟我出去喝点东西么
I don't suppose that you want to have a drink?
当然了 不是喝茶
Not tea, obviously.
跟我去酒吧 喝一杯 今晚
Um, in a pub, with me, tonight.
你不会那么喜欢我的
You wouldn't like me all that much.
喜不喜欢由我自己决定的嘛
Can I maybe decide that for myself?
我不能去
I can't.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
请别再尝试约我了
Please stop asking.
是保安么
Is that security?
有人在么
Hello?
《神探夏洛克》
请工作人员速至收银机…
Can the till supervisor please go to…?
包装区域出现不明货物
Unexpected item in bagging area.
请重试
please try again.
商品未扫描 请重试
Item not scanned. Please try again.
能小点声吗？
Can you maybe keep your voice down?
- 额度不足 信用卡授权失败 - 好吧 我明白了
- Card not authorised. - Yes, all right! I've got it.
请使用其它付款方式 额度不足 信用卡授权失败
Please use an alternative method of payment. Card not authorised.
请使用其它付款方式
Please use an alternative method of payment.
自己留着吧 老子不买了
Keep it. Keep that.
《盲眼银行家》
- 你出去好久 - 是啊 但我啥都没买成
- You took your time. - Yeah, I didn't get the shopping.
什么 怎么了？
What? Why not?
因为我在商店里跟自动收银机吵了一架
Because I had a row in the shop with a chip and PIN machine.
你…你跟台机器吵了一架？
You… You had a row with a machine?!
差不多 它不动弹
Sort of. It sat there.
我朝它叫骂 你有现金么？
and I shouted abuse. Have you got cash?
用我的卡吧
Take my card.
你该自己去的
You could always go yourself, you know,
你在这坐了一上午
you've been sitting there all morning,
我出门这么长时间 你就没挪过窝
you've not even moved since I left.
上次找你办的那个案子呢？
And what happened about that case you were offered…
- 切里亚的钻石？- 没兴趣
- the Jharia diamond? - Not interested.
我给过他们答复了
I sent them a message.
不劳您大驾 我能提得动
Don't worry about me, I can manage.
- 你用的是我的电脑？- 当然了
- Is that my computer? - Of course.
- 什么 - 我的在卧室呢
- What? - Mine was in the bedroom.
什么 就这么两步你都懒得走么？
What? And you couldn't be bothered to get up?
我设了开机密码的
It's password protected.
不妨说 我一分钟内就猜到了
In a manner of speaking. Took me less than a minute to guess yours,
不是什么碉堡嘛
not exactly Fort Knox.
好吧 还来
Right. Thank you.
- 得找个工作了 - 没劲
- Need to get a job. - Oh, dull.
听着 是…
Listen, um…
如果你能借我点儿…
…if you'd be able to lend me some…
- 夏洛克 你在听我说话么 - 我得去趟银行
- Sherlock, are you listening? - I need to go to the bank.
对了 你所谓去银行…
Yes, when you said we were going to the bank…
夏洛克·福尔摩斯
Sherlock Holmes.
- 塞巴斯汀 - 好啊 哥们
- Sebastian. - Hiya, buddy.
好久不见了 算算该有八年了吧？
How long… eight years since I last clapped eyes on you?
这是我朋友 约翰·华生
This is my friend, John Watson.
- 朋友？- 同事
- Friend? - Colleague.
好吧
Right.
随便坐
Grab a pew.
喝点什么 咖啡还是水？
Do you need anything, coffee, water?
- 不需要么 - 我们不渴 谢了
- No? - We're all sorted here, thanks.
看来你过得挺滋润啊 经常出国
So you're doing well. You've been abroad a lot.
怎么说？
Well, so?
全球飞来飞去 一个月内两次
Flying all the way around the world twice in a month.
哈 我看出来了 你又来了
Right. You're doing that thing.
我们是大学同学 这家伙总耍这种鬼把戏
We were at uni together, and this guy here had a trick he used to do.
才不是什么鬼把戏
It's not a trick.
他看你一眼 就知道你的生平
He could look at you and tell you your whole life story.
是啊 我见识过了
Yes, I've seen him do it.
搞得人人自危 讨嫌的家伙
Put the wind up everybody, we hated him.
我们去学院宴会厅吃早餐
We'd come down to breakfast in the formal hall.
这混蛋就一针见血地指出 你前一天鬼混了
and this freak would know you'd been shagging the previous night.
- 我只是观察细节 - 请指教吧
- I simply observed. - Go on, enlighten me.
每月出差两回 满世界飞 全说中了
Two trips a month, flying all the way around the world, you're quite right.
怎么看出来的？
How could you tell?
别告诉我 是我领带上溅了一滴
Are you going to tell me there's a stain on my tie.
什么曼哈顿产的特制番茄酱？
from some special kind of ketchup you can only buy in Manhattan?
- 不 我… - 那是我鞋上的泥点？
- No, I… - Is it the mud on my shoes?
我刚才在外面跟你秘书聊了会儿
I was just chatting with your secretary outside.
她告诉我的
She told me.
你能赶来我太荣幸了 有人非法闯入银行
I'm glad you could make it over, we've had a break-in.
威廉爵士的办公室 他曾是行长
Sir William's office, the bank's former chairman.
为表纪念 银行保留了他的办公室
The room's been left here like a sort of memorial.
昨晚有人闯入
Someone broke in late last night.
- 偷了什么？- 房间里什么都没少
- What did they steal? - Nothing.
仅仅留了一条讯息
Just left a little message.
六十秒内出现的
60 seconds apart.
有人在午夜闯进这里
So, someone came up here in the middle of the night,
挥洒颜料 一分钟内又离开了
splashed paint around and left within a minute.
有多少种方法进那个办公室？
How many ways into that office?
呵 这就是有意思的地方
Well, that's where this gets really interesting.
银行内部每扇门 都由这台电脑上锁
Every door that opens in this bank, it gets locked right here.
每个步入式柜台 每个洗手间
Every walk-in cupboard, every toilet.
那个门昨晚没有开过？
That door didn't open last night?
我们保安系统有漏洞
There's a hole in our security.
你能找到的话 我们付你
Find it and we'll pay you…
五位数
five figures.
这是预付款
This is an advance.
告诉我他怎么进来的
Tell me how he got in.
更大的数额在后面
There's a bigger one on its way.
我不需要金钱激励 塞巴斯汀
I don't need an incentive, Sebastian.
他 咳咳 他是在开玩笑
He's, er… …he's kidding you, obviously.
暂时由我帮他保管吧
Shall I look after that for him?
谢谢
Thanks.
这个月出国两次
Two trips around the world this month.
你没有问过他的秘书
You didn't ask his secretary,
你那么说 就是想故意惹恼他罢了
you said that just to irritate him.
- 你怎么知道的 - 注意到他的手表了吗？
- How did you know? - Did you see his watch?
他的表怎么了
His watch?
时间是对的 但日期不对
The time was right, but the date was wrong.
日期是两天以前
Said two days ago.
他穿越日界线两次了 还没调回来
Crossed the date line twice and he didn't alter it.
一个月内怎么看出来的？
Within a month? How did you get that?
新款百年灵
New Breitling.
今年二月刚刚上市的
Only came out this February.
好吧 你觉得我们还需要在这继续查么
OK. So do you think we should sniff around here for a bit longer?
我要的线索齐了 多谢
Got everything I need to know already, thanks.
那涂鸦是个讯息
That graffiti was a message.
给银行交易大厅某个员工的
Someone at the bank, working on the trading floors.
只要找到讯息接收方
We find the intended recipient and…
就能牵出留讯息的人了？
They'll lead us to the person who sent it?
当然
Obvious.
交易大厅里有三百名工作人员 该从何找起呢
Well, there's 300 people up there, who was it meant for?
- 柱子 - 什么？
- Pillars. - What?
柱子和屏幕
Pillars and the screens.
很少有地方能看到那涂鸦
Very few places you could see that graffiti from.
范围大大缩小了
That narrows the field considerably.
还有 讯息是在
And, of course, the message was left.
昨晚11点34分留下的 这能说明很多事
at 11.34 last night. That tells us a lot.
是吗？
Does it?
每小时都有人轮班
Traders come to work at all hours.
有些同香港的交易得半夜进行
Some trade with Hong Kong in the middle of the night.
那条讯息是给半夜里来的人看的
That message was intended for somebody who came in at midnight.
黄页上姓凡·库的人不多
Not many Van Coons in the phone book.
出租车
Taxi!
现在怎么办 在这儿呆坐着等他回来么
So what do we do now? Sit here and wait for him to come back?
- 刚搬进来 - 啥？
- Just moved in. - What?
楼上这家 名牌是新的
Floor above, new label.
也可能是刚换
Could have just replaced it.
- 没人那么无聊 - 哪位？
- No-one ever does that. - Hello?
你好 我住你家楼下 我们应该还没见过面
Hi, um, I live in the flat just below you. I don't think we've met.
是啊 呃 我才刚搬进来没几天
No, well, er, I've just moved in.
是这样 我忘记带钥匙了
Actually, I've just locked my keys in my flat.
要我放你进来吗？
Do you want me to buzz you in?
谢了 能顺便借用你家阳台吗？
Yeah. And can we use your balcony?
啊？
What?!
夏洛克
Sherlock?
夏洛克 你没事吧
Sherlock, are you OK?
好吧 等你乐意了再给我开门吧
Yeah, any time you feel like letting me in!
你觉得会是破产吗？
Do you think he'd lost a lot of money?
城市小青年自杀挺常见的
Suicide is pretty common among City boys.
- 还不能确定就是自杀 - 得了
- We don't know that it was suicide. - Come on.
门从里面锁死
The door was locked from the inside,
你是爬阳台进来的
you had to climb down the balcony.
从待洗衣物看来他离开了三天
Been away three days judging by the laundry.
看箱子里 有些东西折的很整齐
Look at the case, there was something tightly packed inside it.
- 多谢 我信你就行了 - 不愿意了？
- Thanks. I'll take your word for it. - Problem?
是啊 我可没绝望到要去翻死人内裤
Yeah, I'm not desperate to root around some bloke's dirty underwear.
银行里的涂鸦 意图何在呢？
Those symbols at the bank, the graffiti, why were they put there?
- 某种密码么 - 显而易见
- Some sort of code? - Obviously.
为什么要画？要交流的话 发电邮啊
Why were they painted? Want to communicate, why not use e-mail?
可能他没有回复
Well, maybe he wasn't answering.
好呀 你跟上了
Oh, good, you follow.
还是不懂
No.
哪种讯息让大家唯恐避之不及？
What kind of a message would everyone try to avoid?
比如今天早上？
What about this morning?
- 你盯着的那些信 - 你说账单？
- Those letters you were looking at? - Bills?
没错 他被威胁了
Yes. He was being threatened.
至少不是煤气公司
Not by the Gas Board.
看看能不能从杯子上提些指纹
…see if we can get prints off this glass.
警官 初次见面
Sergeant, we haven't met.
是啊 我知道你是谁
Yeah, I know who you are.
我希望你最好别碰任何证据
and I would prefer it if you didn't tamper with any of the evidence.
我给雷斯垂德打过电话 他过来了么？
I phoned Lestrade. Is he on his way?
他很忙 这里由我负责
He's busy. I'm in charge.
还有 我不是什么警官 我是迪莫克探长
And it's not Sergeant, it's Detective Inspector Dimmock.
这显然是自杀
We're obviously looking at a suicide.
这似乎是所有证据的唯一解释
It does seem the only explanation of all the facts.
错 这只是解释之一
Wrong, it's one possible explanation.
支持部分证据
of some of the facts.
你有了中意的结论 但你
You've got a solution that you like, but you are choosing.
选择忽略了与之不符的一切
to ignore anything you see that doesn't comply with it.
- 比如？- 伤口在头部右侧
- Like? - Wound's on the right side of his head.
- 所以？- 凡·库是左撇子
- And? - Van Coon was left-handed.
身体得有多柔韧啊
Requires quite a bit of contortion.
- 左撇子？- 你竟然没注意到
- Left-handed? - I'm amazed you didn't notice.
看他家的摆设就知道了
All you have to do is look around this flat.
咖啡桌靠左
Coffee table on the left-hand side,
咖啡杯手柄朝左
coffee mug handle pointing to the left.
电源插头常用左边 纸和笔
Power sockets, habitually used the ones on the left. Pen and paper.
在电话左侧 用右手接电话 左手记录
on the left of the phone. Picked up with his right, took messages with his left.
- 还要继续？- 不了 你已经说明了
- D'you want me to go on? - No, I think you've covered it.
还是继续吧 快说完了
I might as well, I'm almost at the bottom of the list.
面包板上刀和黄油
There's a knife on the breadboard with butter.
放在刀刃右边
on the right side of the blade.
因为他用左手握刀
because he used it with his left. It's highly unlikely.
左撇子很难对头部右侧开枪自杀
that a left-handed man would shoot himself in the right of his head.
结论 有人闯了进来杀害了他
Conclusion, someone broke in here and murdered him…
这才是所有证据的唯一结论
only explanation of all of the facts.
那枪呢？
But the gun?
他知道会有人来杀他
He was waiting for the killer.
- 他被威胁过了 - 什么？
- He'd been threatened. - What?
今天在银行 警告了他一次
Today at the bank, sort of a warning.
袭击者进入时他开了一枪
He fired a shot when his attacker came in.
- 子弹呢 - 从开着的窗户飞了
- And the bullet? - Went through the open window.
拜托
Oh, come on!
这几率该有多小啊
What are the chances of that?!
等着看弹道检测报告吧
Wait until you get the ballistics report.
致命的子弹
The bullet in his brain.
不是他枪里的 我向你保证
wasn't fired from his gun, I guarantee it.
他的门从里反锁了 凶手怎么进来的呢？
If his door was locked from the inside, how did the killer get in?
很好 你终于问了个正确的问题
Good, you're finally asking the right questions.
他几乎是用叉子剪自己的头发
He's left trying to sort of cut his hair with a fork,
也就是根本做不到
which of course can never be done.
涂鸦是用来威胁的
It was a threat, that's what the graffiti meant.
我在开会
I'm kind of in a meeting.
你能先跟我秘书预约一下么
Can you make an appointment with my secretary?
我觉得不能等了 抱歉 塞巴斯汀
I don't think this can wait. Sorry, Sebastian.
你的一位交易员 在你办公室工作的 被谋杀了
One of your traders, someone who worked in your office, was killed.
- 什么？- 凡·库
- What? - Van Coon.
警方正在他家
The police are at his flat.
被谋杀了？抱歉影响了大家的胃口
Killed?! Sorry to interfere with everyone's digestion.
还要预约么
Still want to make an appointment?
要不九点跟苏格兰场警官约一下？
Would maybe nine o'clock at Scotland Yard suit?
哈罗公学 牛津大学 有为青年啊
Harrow, Oxford…very bright guy.
在亚洲工作过 所以…
Worked in Asia for a while, so…
你让他负责香港账户？
You gave him the Hong Kong accounts?
曾经一早上损失了五百万
Lost 5 million in a single morning,
一周内又赚回来了
made it all back a week later.
艾迪有着钢铁般的意志
Nerves of steel, Eddie had.
- 谁会想杀他呢 - 人人都会树敌
- Who'd want to kill him? - We all make enemies.
但不是人人都会被爆头
You don't all end up with a bullet through your temple.
- 常人是不会 - 失陪一下
- Not usually. - Excuse me.
董事长的短信
It's my chairman.
警方找他了
Police have been on to him.
显然 警方说是自杀
Apparently they're telling him it was a suicide.
他们弄错了
Well, they've got it wrong,
塞巴斯汀 他是被谋杀的
Sebastian. He was murdered.
恐怕警方不这么看
Well, I'm afraid they don't see it like that.
- 所以？- 所以我老板也不这么看
- So? - And neither does my boss.
别忘了我雇你查什么的 别分心
I hired you to do a job. Don't get sidetracked.
果然银行家都是铁石心肠的混蛋
I thought bankers were all supposed to be heartless bastards.
我要你跑一趟克里斯宾拍卖行
I need you to get over to Crispians.
有两个明代成化年间的古董花瓶拍卖
Two Ming vases up for auction, Chenghua.
- 你能评估下么 - 应该素琳去啊 她才是专家
- Will you appraise them? - Soo Lin should go, she's the expert.
素琳辞职了 需要你帮忙
Soo Lin has resigned her job. I need you.
- 就是临时工哦 - 嗯 没问题
- Just locum work. - No, that's fine.
你… 其实以你的资历干这个浪费了
You're, um… Well, you're a bit over-qualified.
呃 因为我急需用钱
Er, I could always do with the money.
这周有两位医师度假去了
Well, we've got two away on holiday this week.
还有一位因为怀孕离职了
and one's just left to have a baby.
对你来说可能太平凡了
It might be a bit mundane for you.
不不不 有时候平凡点也是好事
Er, no, mundane is good, sometimes.
我挺喜欢平凡
Mundane works.
- 简历上说你曾经是个军人 - 军医
- It says here you were a soldier. - And a doctor.
你还会别的技能么？
Anything else you can do?
在学校学过单簧管
I learned the clarinet at school.
呵呵 期待你的表演哦
Oh…well, I'll look forward to it.
我说过了 你能给我递支笔么
I said, could you pass me a pen?
- 什么 啥时候？- 大概一小时以前
- What? When? - About an hour ago.
根本没注意我已经出门了吗？
Didn't notice I'd gone out then?
我去一家诊所面试了
I went to see about a job at that surgery.
- 怎么样 - 棒极了 她很迷人
- How was it? - Great. She's great.
谁？
Who?
工作
The job.
她？
She?!
它
It.
随便了 过来看
Yeah, have a look.
「能穿墙的侵入者」
"The intruder who can walk through walls."
昨天晚上的事
It happened last night.
一记者在家中遭枪击身亡
Journalist shot dead in his flat.
房内门窗皆从内反锁
Doors locked, windows bolted from the inside.
跟凡·库一样
Exactly the same as Van Coon.
- 天哪 你是说… - 凶手又得手了
- God! You think…? - He's killed another one.
布莱恩·卢奇 自由职业记者
Brian Lukis, freelance journalist,
在自己家被杀
murdered in his flat.
房门从内紧锁
Doors locked from the inside.
你得承认 两次很相似
You've got to admit, it's similar.
两人都是被能穿水泥墙的凶手杀的
Both men killed by someone who can walk through solid walls.
探长 你真认为艾迪·凡·库的死
Inspector, do you seriously believe that Eddie Van Coon was.
仅仅是一起都市自杀？
just another city suicide?
我猜你该看过弹道检测报告了吧
You have seen the ballistics report, I suppose?
杀害他的子弹 是出自他的枪口么
And the shot that killed him. Was it fired from his own gun?
不
No.
不 所以这案子进程本来
No. So this investigation might move.
会快很多 要是你们当初相信我的话
a bit quicker if you were to take my word as gospel.
我刚向你递交了谋杀调查申请
I've just handed you a murder inquiry.
请给我五分钟调查死者公寓
Five minutes in his flat.
四楼
Four floors up.
所以他们自认为安全了
That's why they think they're safe.
门链搭上 门闩上 就认为固若金汤了
Put a chain across the door, bolt it shut, think they're impregnable.
他们根本没考虑 还有别的方法进入房间
They don't reckon for one second that there's another way in.
- 我不懂 - 这是个飞檐走壁的凶手
- I don't understand. - Dealing with a killer who can climb.
- 你到底在干嘛 - 凶手能像昆虫一样攀墙
- What are you doing? - Clings to the walls like an insect.
这就是他的入口
That's how he got in.
什么？
What?!
他沿墙而上 跑过屋顶
He climbed up the side of the walls, ran along the roof,
从天窗跳了进来
dropped in through this skylight.
你开玩笑吧 蜘蛛侠吗？
You're not serious?! Like Spider-Man?
他爬上了港口住宅区公寓六楼
He scaled six floors of a Docklands apartment building,
- 从阳台跳进去杀了凡·库 - 鬼扯
- jumped the balcony and killed Van Coon. - Oh, hold on!
他也是这么进银行的 沿着窗架攀进露台
That's how he got into the bank, ran along the window ledge onto the terrace.
我得找到这两个受害人的联系
I have to find out what connects these two men.
借书卡上敲的日期是他被杀当天
Date stamped on the book is the same day that he died.
夏洛克？
Sherlock?
好 杀手到银行
So, the killer goes to the bank,
留下了威胁密码
leaves a threatening cipher at the bank.
凡·库看到后惊慌失措 跑回自己家锁上门
Van Coon panics, returns to his apartment, locks himself in.
几小时后 他被杀害
Hours later, he dies.
凶手在图书馆发现了卢奇 把密码写在
The killer finds Lukis at the library, he writes the cipher.
他一定会看到的书架上
on the shelf where he knows it'll be seen.
卢奇逃回家里
Lukis goes home.
深夜 同样被杀害
Late that night, he dies too.
他们为什么会被杀 夏洛克？
Why did they die, Sherlock?
只有密码能告诉我们
Only the cipher can tell us.
世界全靠编码和密码运转 约翰
The world's run on codes and ciphers, John.
从价值百万的银行报警系统
From the million-pound security system at the bank.
到你欺负的条码扫描仪
to the PIN machine you took exception to.
我们身边密码术无处不在
Cryptography inhabits our every waking moment.
是 我知道 但是…
Yes, OK, but…
都是电脑生成的
But it's all computer generated…
电子编译 电子密码
electronic codes, electronic ciphering methods.
这次的不同
This is different.
这是古代手法
It's an ancient device.
现代编译法没用
Modern code-breaking methods won't unravel it.
- 我们这是去哪？- 我要去咨询个人
- Where are we headed? - I need to ask some advice.
什么？不好意思再说一遍？
What?! Sorry?
你听清楚了 我死都不说了
You heard me perfectly. I'm not saying it again.
- 你咨询别人？- 是颜料
- You need advice? - On painting.
对 我得问问专家
Yes, I need to talk to an expert.
新系列的一部分
Part of a new exhibition.
- 很有意思 - 我命名它为
- Interesting. - I call it…
城市嗜血狂
Urban Bloodlust Frenzy.
朗朗上口
Catchy!
我只有两分钟 社区协警
I've got two minutes before a Community Support Officer.
就要转过那墙角来了
comes around that corner.
我画着 你说？
Can we do this while I'm working?
- 你知道这谁画的么 - 我认得这颜料
- Know the author? - I recognise the paint.
像密歇根产的 喷力强劲
It's like Michigan…hard-core propellant.
我猜含锌
I'd say zinc.
那个符号呢 你认识么
And what about the symbols? Do you recognise them?
都不知是不是个符号
I'm not even sure it's a proper language.
两个人被杀了 莱兹
Two men have been murdered, Raz.
破解这密码是找到凶手的关键
Deciphering this is the key to finding out who killed them.
这是你们唯一的线索？
And this is all you've got to go on?
- 好像不太够吧 - 你到底帮不帮忙？
- It's hardly much, is it? - Are you going to help us or not?
我帮你问问
I'll ask around.
- 肯定有人知道点什么 - 喂
- Somebody must know something about it. - Oi!
你他妈的在干什么？
What the hell do you think you're doing?
这画廊是登记保护建筑
This gallery is a listed public building.
不不 等等 不是我画的
No, no. Wait, wait. It's not me who painted that.
我只是帮着拿一下…
I was just holding this for…
还是个狂热分子哈？
Bit of an enthusiast, are we?
她手上有个重要修复项目 才进行到一半
She was right in the middle of an important piece of restoration.
她不可能突然辞职的
Why would she suddenly resign?
家庭纠纷 她辞呈里说的
Family problems. She said so in her letter.
但她没家庭啊
But she doesn't have a family.
她独自来这个国家的
She came to this country on her own.
- 安迪 - 那些茶壶 那些陶瓷
- Andy! - Look, those teapots, those ceramics.
已经成了她的心头宝
They've become her obsession.
她都修复它们好几周了
She's been working on restoring them for weeks.
我不信她会突然…抛下它们
I can't believe that she would just…abandon them.
也许是想躲开某个缠着她的人呢？
Perhaps she was getting a bit of unwanted attention?
你怎么这么慢
You've been a while.
是啊 你知道的嘛
Yeah, well, you know how it is.
拘留所警官都是慢性子 对吧
Custody sergeants don't really like to be hurried, do they?
走程序呗 按指纹
Just formalities. Fingerprints,
签罚单 周二我还得上治安法庭
charge sheet, and I've got to be in magistrates' court on Tuesday.
- 嗯？- 我 夏洛克 我周二要上庭
- What? - Me, Sherlock! In court, on Tuesday!
- 他们要判我反社会行为罪 - 可以 很好
- They're giving me an ASBO! - Good, fine.
你告诉你那小朋友
You want to tell your little pal.
欢迎他随时去自首
he's welcome to go and own up any time.
这个符号 我还是搞不明白
This symbol, I still can't place it.
不 我要你去趟警察局
No, I need you to go to the police station.
问问那记者的事
and ask about the journalist.
他的个人财物应该存档了
The personal effects will have been impounded.
去把他的日记 或别的什么记录行程的拿来
Get hold of his diary, or something that will tell us his movements.
去找凡·库的助理
Go and see Van Coon's PA.
追踪他们的行程 总会找到重合的
If you retrace their steps, somewhere they'll coincide.
苏格兰场
Scotland Yard.
周五从大连飞回来的
Flew back from Dalian Friday.
看来他跟销售连开了几场会
Looks like he had back-to-back meetings with the sales team.
能给我打印一份么
Can you print me up a copy?
- 没问题 - 他去世那天呢？
- Sure. What - About the day he died?
你能告诉我他在哪吗？
Can you tell me where he was?
抱歉 这有个空当
Sorry, I've got a gap.
我有他所有的收据
I have all his receipts.
- 你的朋友… - 听着 不管你说什么
- Your friend… - Listen, whatever you say,
我都百分百赞成
I'm behind you 100 per cent.
是个自大的混蛋
…he's an arrogant sod.
就这样而已？别人说得可要难听多了
Well, that was mild. People say a lot worse than that.
你是来要这个的吧 那记者的日记
This is what you wanted, isn't it? The journalist's diary?
他做老板如何 阿曼达？欣赏员工么？
What kind of a boss was he, Amanda? Appreciative?
不 我可不会用这个词
Um, no. That's not a word I'd use.
艾迪只欣赏带天价标签的东西
The only things Eddie appreciated had a big price tag.
比如那瓶护手霜 是他给你买的吧
Like that hand cream. He bought that for you, didn't he?
看这个
Look at this one.
他去世那天叫过出租车 18.5镑
Got a taxi from him on the day he died, 18.50.
是送他去办公室的
That would get him to the office.
不是交通高峰 看看时间
Not rush hour. Check the time.
正在早上 18镑他能到…
Mid-morning. 18 would get him.
最远到… 西区
as far as… … The West End.
我记得他说过
I remember him saying.
地铁票 一点钟在皮卡迪利广场买的
Underground, printed at one in Piccadilly.
他最终是搭地铁回的办公室
So he got a Tube back to the office.
他为什么要搭出租进城 搭地铁回来呢？
Why would he get a taxi into town, and then the Tube back?
因为他在送一件重物
Because he was delivering something heavy.
扛着个大包裹上电梯很不方便
You wouldn't lug a package up the escalator.
送东西？
Delivering?!
送给皮卡迪利广场地铁站附近某人
To somewhere near Piccadilly Station.
把包裹放下 送到手 然后…
Dropped the package, delivered it, and then…
停了一下 他饿了
Stopped on his way. He got peckish.
于是你在去地铁站的路上买了午饭
So you bought your lunch from here en route to the station.
但是你从哪过来的呢？
but where were you headed from?
你从哪下的出租车？
Where did the taxi drop you?
哦 对了
Oof! Right.
艾迪·凡·库死的那天 送了个包裹来
Eddie Van Coon brought a package here the day he died.
不管那箱子里是什么
Whatever was hidden inside that case…
我已经拼出了一幅拼图
I've managed to piece together a picture.
用零碎信息 信用卡账单 收据
using scraps of information, credit card bills, receipts.
他从中国回来
He flew back from China,
- 就来了这里 - 夏洛克
- then he came here. - Sherlock.
就在这街上 附近
Somewhere in this street, somewhere near.
不知具体在哪 可…
I don't know where, but…
- 就在那儿的那个商店 - 你怎么知道？
- That shop, over there. - How could you tell?
卢奇的日记 他那天也在
Lukis' diary. He was here too.
- 他记下了地址 - 哦
- He wrote down the address. - Oh.
你好
Hello.
想要…招财猫吗？
You want…lucky cat?
不 不用了 谢谢
No, thanks, no.
只要10镑啊 只要10镑
10! 10 pounds.
我觉得你老婆 她会喜欢
I think your wife, she will like.
呃 谢谢
Um, thank you.
夏洛克…
Sherlock…
- 这个标签 - 没错 我看见了
- The label there. - Yes, I see it.
跟密码上一模一样
It's exactly the same as the cipher.
这是个古老的号码系统 「苏州码子」
It's an ancient number system, Hang Zhou.
如今只有街头贩子才用
These days only street traders use it.
这就是银行
Those were numbers written on the wall at the bank.
图书馆墙上写的数字
and at the library.
用古老的中国异体字写的数字
Numbers written in an ancient Chinese dialect.
这个是15
It's a 15.
我们以为是商标的 其实是数字15
What we thought was the artist's tag, it's a number 15.
蒙眼布 那条水平线也是数字
And the blindfold, the horizontal line. That was a number as well.
是汉字的1 约翰 我们找到了
The Chinese number one, John. We found it.
两个从中国回来的人
Two men travel back from China,
都直奔招财猫商店而去
both head straight for the Lucky Cat emporium.
他们看到了什么？
What did they see?
不因为他们看到了什么
It's not what they saw.
是他们箱子里拿回来的东西
It's what they both brought back in those suitcases.
你说的不是机场免税品吧
And you don't mean duty free.
谢谢
Thank you.
想想塞巴斯汀说的
Think about what Sebastian told us.
关于凡·库的 他在市场上处于机动状态
About Van Coon, about how he stayed afloat in the market.
- 损失五百万 - 一星期又赚回来了
- Lost 5 million. - Made it back in a week.
这就是他赚钱的窍门
That's how he made such easy money.
- 他是个走私者 - 嗯
- He was a smuggler. - Mm.
有完美的掩护
Cover would have been perfect.
商人 经常去亚洲
Businessman, making frequent trips to Asia.
卢奇也是 采写中国新闻的记者
Lukis was the same, a journalist writing about China.
他们俩都从事走私
Both of them smuggled stuff about.
招财猫是他们的交货地
The Lucky Cat was their drop-off.
但他们为什么会死呢？
But why did they die?
没道理啊
It doesn't make sense.
如果他们来商店 送到了货
If they both turn up at the shop and deliver the goods,
为什么有人威胁他们
why would someone threaten them.
还要杀人灭口 他们已经完成任务了啊
and kill them after the event, after they'd finished the job?
如果他们之一雁过拔毛了呢？
What if one of them was light-fingered?
- 什么意思？- 偷了东西
- How do you mean? - Stole something.
从那批货里
Something from the hoard.
但凶手不知道谁偷的
The killer doesn't know which of them took it.
- 于是威胁他们两个 - 没错
- so threatens them both. - Right.
替我想想
Remind me.
上次下雨是什么时候？
When was the last time that it rained?
从周一就在这儿了
It's been here since Monday.
（姚素琳）
至少三天内 没人进过那公寓的门
No-one's been in that flat for at least three days.
可能是度假去了
Could have gone on holiday.
你度假去不关窗户吗？
Do you leave your windows open when you go on holiday?
夏洛克
Sherlock!
有人来过这
Someone else has been here.
有人闯进公寓 打翻了花瓶
Somebody else broke into the flat and knocked over the vase,
就像我一样
just like I did.
这次总能先让我进来吧？
Do you think maybe you could let me in this time?
你别老这样行不行？
Can you not keep doing this, please?
我不是第一个来的
I'm not the first.
- 什么？- 有人在我之前来过了
- What? - Somebody's been in here before me.
你在说什么？
What are you saying?
八号鞋
Size eight feet.
小个子 但…强健灵巧
Small, but…athletic.
我真是白费唾沫
I'm wasting my breath.
小而有力的手
Small, strong hands.
我们找到个杂技演员啊
Our acrobat.
他走时为什么不关窗？
Why didn't he close the window when he lef…?
哦 真蠢 太蠢了
Oh, stupid, stupid!
这是显然的
Obvious.
他还在这里
He's still here.
你随时想要带上我的话…
Any time you want to include me…
约翰…
John…
约翰
John!
哦 我是夏洛克·福尔摩斯 我总是单枪匹马
Oh, I'm Sherlock Holmes and I always work alone.
因为谁也跟不上我出色的头脑
because no-one else can compete with my massive intellect!
牛奶坏了 脏衣服也有味了
The milk's gone off and the washing's started to smell.
- 有人三天前匆忙离开了 - 有人？
- Somebody left here in a hurry three days ago. - Somebody?
姚素琳 我们得找到她
Soo Lin Yao. We have to find her.
到底要怎么找啊？
How, exactly?
（素琳 打电话给我报个平安 安迪）
（国家古董博物馆）
从这个开始
We could start with this.
你咳嗽这么厉害 是不是感冒了啊？
You've gone all croaky. Are you getting a cold?
我没事
I'm fine.
你上次看到她是什么时候？
When was the last time that you saw her?
三天前 就在博物馆
Three days ago. Here at the museum.
今天早上他们说 她辞职了
This morning they told me she'd resigned.
忽然就走了 工作都没做完
Just like that. Left her work unfinished.
她在这最后一下午 最后一件事是什么？
What was the last thing that she did on her final afternoon?
为游客做表演 演示茶艺
She does this demonstration for the tourists, a tea ceremony.
于是她有可能把东西打包起来先放在这里了
So she would have packed up her things and just put them in here.
我们必须找到姚素琳
We have to get to Soo Lin Yao.
- 如果她还活着的话 - 夏洛克
- If she's still alive. - Sherlock!
哇 瞧瞧这是谁
Oh, look who it is.
有你可能感兴趣的东西
Found something you'll like.
星期二早晨
Tuesday morning,
你只要出庭 说包是你的就行了
all you've got to do is turn up and say the bag was yours.
别管什么出庭了
Forget about your court date.
伙计 你真牛啊！
Dude, that was rad!
藏一棵树 最好的地方是森林里
You want to hide a tree, then a forest is the best place to do it,
不是吗？
wouldn't you say?
人们只会毫不注意地走过去
People would just walk straight past, not knowing,
完全无法解密你的信息
unable to decipher the message.
就在那儿 我刚才就看见了
There. I spotted it earlier.
- 他们来过 - 颜料也一样吧？
- They've been here. - And that's the exact same paint?
是的
Yeah.
约翰 想要破解这个密码
John, if we're going to decipher this code,
我们必须找更多证据
we need to look for more evidence.
接电话 我打了半天了
Answer your phone. I've been calling you.
我找到了
I found it.
被盖掉了
It's been painted over.
我不明白 刚才…
I don't understand. It was…
还在这儿
here.
10分钟前 我还看见的
10 minutes ago. I saw it.
一大片涂鸦
A whole load of graffiti.
有人不想我看到它们
Somebody doesn't want me to see it.
- 夏洛克 - 嘘
- Sherlock. - Ssh!
- 你干什么？- 约翰 集中精神
- What are you doing…? - John, concentrate.
我要你非常专心 闭上眼睛
I need you to concentrate. Close your eyes.
怎么了？为什么…你要干吗？
What? Why? Why? What are you doing?
我需要你将你的图像记忆最大化
I need you to maximise your visual memory.
把你看到的描绘出来
Try to picture what you saw.
- 你能描绘出来吗？- 能
- Can you picture it? - Yeah.
- 你能记得吗？- 肯定能
- Can you remember it? - Yes, definitely.
你记得图案吗？
Can you remember the pattern?
- 记得 - 你能记得多少？
- Yes. - How much can you remember it?
你别急呀
Look, don't worry.
因为一般人类的图像记忆
Because the average human memory on visual matters.
只有62%准确度
is only 62% accurate.
- 别担心 我都记得呢 - 真的？
- Well, don't worry, I remember all of it. - Really?
至少 让我掏掏口袋就行
At least I would, if I could get to my pockets.
我拍照了
I took a photograph.
全都是成对的 约翰 瞧这个
Always in pairs, John, look.
数字…
Numbers…
和图案搭配
come with partners.
天啊 我好困
God, I need to sleep.
为什么画在贴轨道的地方？
Why did he paint it so near the tracks?
不知道
No idea.
每天有无数人经过这里
Thousands of people pass by there every day.
哪怕只20分钟…
Just 20 minutes…
当然了
Of course.
当然了 他要消息 他只是在
Of course, he wants information. He's trying to communicate.
与地下世界的朋友通讯
with his people in the underworld.
不管被偷的是什么 他想要回来
Whatever was stolen, he wants it back.
就在这里 这是个密码
It's somewhere here, in a code.
没有姚素林 我们没法破解它
We can't crack this without Soo Lin Yao.
哦 好吧
Oh, good.
两个从中国回来的男人被谋杀了
Two men who travelled back from China were murdered.
凶手用苏州码子留下了口信
And their killer left them messages in Hang Zhou numerals.
姚素林现在很危险
Soo Lin Yao is in danger.
这个密码和其他的口信都是同一个意思
That cipher, it was just the same pattern as the others.
他想要把她也杀了
He means to kill her as well.
听着 我到处都问过了…
Look, I've tried everywhere…
朋友 同事 我不知她哪里去了
friends, colleagues. I don't know where she's gone.
我是说 她可能早在千里之外了
I mean, she could be a thousand miles away.
你看什么？
What are you looking at?
跟我讲讲那些茶壶吧
Tell me more about those teapots.
她对茶壶非常着迷 它们急需修复
The pots were her obsession. They need urgent work.
如果过干 陶土就会开始裂缝
If they dry out, then the clay can start to crumble.
显然 你必须不停地用它泡茶
Apparently, you have to just keep making tea in them.
昨天 这些壶里只有一个是有光泽的
Yesterday, only one of those pots was shining.
现在有两个了
Now, there are two.
想吃块午茶饼干吗？
Fancy a biscuit with that?
几百年的东西了 我可不想打破它
Centuries old. Don't want to break that.
你好
Hello.
你看到了密码
You saw the cipher.
然后你就知道他是冲我来的了
Then you know he is coming for me.
直到现在为止 你躲避他的策略还都很聪明
You've been clever to avoid him so far.
我必须完成它
I had to finish.
完成我的工作
To finish this work.
早晚注定的
It's only a matter of time.
他总会找到我
I know he will find me.
他是谁？你见过他吗？
Who is he? Have you met him before?
我小时候 在中国认识了他
When I was a girl, we met in China.
我认出了他的…
I recognised his…
- 签名 - 那个密码？
- Signature. - The cipher?
只有他会这样 蜘蛛
Only he would do this. Zhi Zhu.
- 蜘蛛？- 中文的蜘蛛
- Zhi Zhu? - The spider.
你认得这个标志吗？
You know this mark?
对 这是一个堂口的标志
Yes. It's the mark of a Tong.
- 什么？- 古老的黑帮组织
- Huh? - Ancient crime syndicate,
源自中国
based in China.
每个喽啰都有这个标志
Every foot soldier bears the mark.
每个为他们运货的人
Everyone who hauls for them.
运货？
Hauls?
你是说你也做走私？
You mean you were a smuggler?
那时我只有15岁
I was 15.
父母双亡
My parents were dead.
无依无靠
I had no livelihood.
每日无法谋生
No way of surviving, day-to-day,
只有为黑帮大哥工作
except to work for the bosses.
他们都是谁？
Who are they?
他们号称黑莲帮
They are called the Black Lotus.
到了我16岁时
By the time I was 16,
我已经把价值几千镑的毒品
I was taking thousands of pounds worth of drugs.
带入香港境内了
across the border into Hong Kong.
但我结束了那段生活
I managed to leave that life behind me.
我来到了英国
I came to England.
在这里 我找到了工作
They gave me a job, here.
一切都好起来了 全新的生活
Everything was good. New life.
然后他就来找你了
And he came looking for you.
是的
Yes.
我本希望 在五年之后…
I hoped, after five years…
也许他们已经忘了我
maybe they would have forgotten me.
但他们从不会真正放你走
But they never really let you leave.
我们这么小的社群中
A small community like ours…
他们其实一直如影随形
…they are never very far away.
他来到我的公寓
He came to my flat.
要我帮他找些被偷走的东西
He asked me to help him to track down something that was stolen.
你并不知道要找什么？
And you've no idea what it was?
我拒绝帮他找
I refused to help.
那么 当年你在中国 与他交情很深咯？
So, you knew him well when you were living back in China?
哦 当然
Oh, yes.
他是我的亲哥哥
He's my brother.
两个孤儿
Two orphans.
我们别无选择
We had no choice.
要么为黑莲帮卖命
We could work for the Black Lotus,
要么像乞丐一样饿死街头
or starve on the streets, like beggars.
我哥哥成了他们的喽啰
My brother has become their puppet.
在一个姓单的人手下做事
In the power of the one they call Shan.
黑莲帮的帮主
The Black Lotus general.
我赶走了哥哥
I turned my brother away.
他说我背叛了他
He said I had betrayed him.
第二天 我来上班
Next day, I came to work.
一眼就看到了那密码
and the cipher was waiting.
你能破解吗？
Can you decipher these?
- 都是数字 - 这个我知道
- These are numbers. - Yes, I know.
这里 穿过人眼的横线 代表中文的数字一
Here, the line across the man's eyes, it's the Chinese number one.
这个是个15 但是怎样解码呢？
And this one is 15. But what's the code?
所有的走私者都知道
All the smugglers know it.
是按照一本书…
It's based upon a book…
他来了
He's here.
蜘蛛找到我了
Zhi Zhu has found me.
不 别去 夏洛克
No, no, Sherlock.
夏洛克 等等
Sherlock, wait!
过来
Come here.
进来 快进来
Get in. Get in!
我得去帮他 我走后锁好门
I have to go and help him. Bolt the door after me.
小心
Careful!
这有些头骨已经20多万年了
Some of those skulls are over 200, 000 years old.
拜托有点敬畏之心
Have a bit of respect.
谢谢
Thank you.
梁
Liang.
大哥
SPEAKS CHINESE.
是你
哦 天啊
Oh, my God.
到底要几起凶案发生
How many murders is it going to take.
你才相信一个疯子在到处杀人啊？
before you start believing that this maniac's out there?
今晚一个女孩中枪了
A young girl was gunned down tonight.
三天三个受害者
That's three victims in three days.
你应该正在满世界找他才对
You're supposed to be finding him.
布莱恩·卢奇和艾迪·凡·库
Brian Lukis and Eddie Van Coon.
为一伙跨国走私者工作
were working for a gang of international smugglers.
他们号称黑莲帮 在伦敦秘密活动
A gang called the Black Lotus, operating here in London.
就在你鼻子底下作乱
right under your nose.
你有证据吗？
Can you prove that?
你想吃什么 猪肉还是意大利面？
What are you thinking? Pork or pasta?
哦 是你啊
Oh, it's you.
这不需要五星级美食家来决定吧
I suppose it's never going to trouble Egon Ronay, is it?
我推荐意大利面
I'd stick with the pasta.
还是别吃烤猪排了
Don't want to be doing roast pork,
整天都在解剖尸体
not if you're slicing up cadavers.
你吃什么？
What are you having?
我工作时不吃饭 消化让我迟钝
I don't eat when I'm working. Digesting slows me down.
你今晚要在这工作？
So you're working here tonight?
- 有些尸体要检查 - 有些？
- Need to examine some bodies. - Some?
布莱恩·卢奇和艾迪·凡·库
Eddie Van Coon and Brian Lukis.
都在我名单上呢
They're on my list.
能把他们推出来 再让我看一眼吗？
Could you wheel them out again for me?
呃…他们的档案已经送审了
Well…their paperwork's already gone through.
- 你的头发变了嘛 - 什么？
- You changed your hair. - What?
你换了发型 以前都从中间分开的
The style. It's usually parted in the middle.
是啊 这个…
Yes, well…
挺好看的
It's good.
这个发型…更适合你
It…suits you better this way.
我们只想看一眼脚
We're just interested in the feet.
- 脚？- 是啊
- The feet? - Yes.
介不介意我看一眼呢？
Do you mind if we have a look at them?
现在 来看凡·库
Now, Van Coon.
哦 那么…
Oh! So…
要么这两人碰巧去的
So either these two men just happened to visit.
同一家中国纹身店
the same Chinese tattoo parlour,
- 要么我说的是真的 - 你想怎样？
- or I'm telling the truth. - What do you want?
我想要卢奇和凡·库两人家所有的书
I want every book from Lukis' apartment and Van Coon's.
书？
Their books?
他们不只是个犯罪团伙 还是个邪教
Not just a criminal organisation. It's a cult.
她哥哥就是被头目之一拉拢的
Her brother was corrupted by one of its leaders.
素琳说了那人的名字
Soo Lin said the name.
是的 单 单帮主
Yes, Shan. General Shan.
我们对他一点线索也没有
We're still no closer to finding him.
错 我们的信息已经快全了
Wrong! We've got almost all we need to know.
她把我们缺的那几块基本补上了
She gave us most of the missing pieces.
他为什么要去见他妹妹呢？
Why did he need to visit his sister?
他为什么需要她的知识？
Why did he need her expertise?
她在博物馆工作啊
She worked at the museum.
- 没错 - 她是古董专家
- Exactly. - An expert in antiquities.
- 当然 懂了 - 是古董 约翰
- Of course, I see. - Valuable antiquities, John.
珍贵中国文物 在黑市上购买的
Ancient Chinese relics purchased on the black market.
毛的革命之后 那里埋藏了无数珍宝
China's home to a thousand treasures hidden after Mao's revolution.
黑莲帮正在兜售它们
The Black Lotus is selling them.
看看日期…这里
Check for the dates… Here,
约翰 「四天前自中国运进」
John, "arrived from China four days ago".
没有名字
Anonymous.
卖方不透露自己的身份
The vendor doesn't give his name.
「两件来自东方 埋藏多年的宝物」
"Two undiscovered treasures from the East."
一件在卢奇箱子里 另一件在凡·库那里
One in Lukis' suitcase and one in Van Coon's.
「古董…」
"Antiquities…
「顺利拍出」
"sold at auction."
瞧 又有一个
Look, here's another one.
一个月前自中国运进
Arrived from China a month ago,
中国陶瓷雕像 卖了40万镑
Chinese ceramic statue sold for 400, 000.
再看 又一个月前 中国古画50万镑
Look, a month before that, Chinese painting, 500, 000.
所有这些 都来自匿名的卖家
All of them from an anonymous source.
他们正从中国一件件地偷运文物
They're stealing them back in China.
卖到英国来
and one by one feeding them into Britain.
每次拍卖的日期
Every single auction coincides.
都和卢奇与凡·库去中国的时间相符
with Lukis or Van Coon travelling to China.
那如果他们之一在中国见财起意呢？
So what if one of them got greedy when they were in China?
如果他们之一偷了东西呢？
What if one of them stole something?
这就是蜘蛛找上门的原因
That's why Zhi Zhu's come.
抱歉 我们在为慈善筹款吗 夏洛克？
Sorry, are we collecting for charity, Sherlock?
什么？
What?
门外有个年轻人 搬了几箱子书
A young man's outside with crates of books.
那么数字是查询码
So the numbers are references.
查询书的？
To books?
以这种方式标明页码 和具体的词
To specific pages and specific words on those pages.
好的 那么…
Right, so…
15和1 意思是？
15 and 1, that means?
15页 第一个词
Turn to page 15 and it's the first word you read.
好吧 信息是什么？
OK, so what's the message?
要看是哪本书了
Depends on the book.
这就是图书密码的狡猾之处
That's the cunning of the book code.
得是他俩都有的书
It has to be one that they both own.
那好吧 看样子还挺好找的 是吧？
OK, fine. This shouldn't take too long, should it?
我们在博物馆找到了这些 是你的笔迹吗？
We found these…at the museum. Is this your writing?
我们希望素琳能帮我们解码
Er, we hoped Soo Lin could decipher it for us.
谢了
Ta.
还要我做什么？
Anything else I can do?
我是说 还有什么能效劳
To assist you, I mean.
你要能安静一会儿 就最好不过了
Some silence right now would be marvellous.
香烟
Cigarette.
想象
Imagine.
抱歉让你们久等
I'm sorry to keep you waiting,
但是医生直到下周四都没有空闲
but we haven't got anything now until next Thursday.
真是慢死了
This is taking ages.
抱歉
Sorry.
如果他们老这么言而无信 何必预约呢？
What's the point of booking an appointment if they can't stick to it?
呃 怎么了？
Um, what's going on?
你雇的那个新医生好久没让病人进去了
That new doctor you hired, he hasn't buzzed the intercom for ages.
我去跟他说说
Let me go and have a word.
- 借过 - 抱歉
- Excuse me. - Sorry.
约翰？
John?
看来我已经完事了 我以为我还有病人呢
Looks like I'm done. I thought I had some more to see.
- 哦 我帮你看了一两个 - 一两个？
- Oh, I did one or two of yours. - One or two?
好吧 也许是五六个
Well, maybe five or six.
抱歉 我真是太不专业了
I'm sorry, that's not very professional.
不 没什么
No, not really.
我…昨晚熬夜有点晚了
I had…a bit of a late one.
哦 好吧
Oh, right.
反正 再见啦
Anyway, see you.
那么…你昨晚为什么熬夜呢？
So…what were you doing to keep you up so late?
我参加了一个…读书活动
I was attending a sort of book event.
这样啊 她很喜欢读书吧
Oh. Oh, she likes books,
我是说你女朋友？
does she, your girlfriend?
没 我不是去约会的
No, it wasn't a date.
很好 我是说 我…
Good. I mean, I'm…
我今晚也没有约会
And I don't have one tonight.
一本人人都有的书
A book that everybody would own.
15页 第一行
15, entry 1.
（增加）
（鼻孔）
（我）
我需要新鲜空气 咱们今晚出去转转
I need to get some air. We're going out tonight.
- 其实 我有个约会 - 啥？
- Actually, I've got a date. - What?
两个彼此喜欢的人 出去一起玩那种？
Where two people who like each other go out and have fun?
我就是建议我们去呀
That's what I was suggesting.
不 你说的不是 至少我希望…不是
No, it wasn't. At least, I hope not.
你带她去哪？
Where are you taking her?
呃 看电影吧
Er, cinema.
没劲 无聊 毫无新意…
Dull, boring, predictable…
试试这个怎么样？
Why don't you try this?
只在伦敦上演一晚哦
In London for one night only.
谢了 但我不是来找你请教约会的
Thanks, but I don't come to you for dating advice.
很多年没人带我来看马戏了
It's years since anyone took me to the circus.
是么 好啊
Right, yes.
一个朋友推荐的 我就打电话订了票
A friend recommended it to me and I phoned up.
哦 是什么剧团啊 世界巡演吗？
Oh! What are they, a touring company or something?
我其实也不知道
I don't know much about it.
我想他们可能是从中国来的
I think they're probably from China.
我想也是 真是太巧了
I think so, yes. There's a coincidence!
太好了 多谢你
That's wonderful, thank you very much.
你好 我订了两张今晚的票
Hi, I have two tickets reserved for tonight.
- 什么名字？- 福尔摩斯
- And what's the name? - Holmes.
哦 这个名字订了三张票
Actually, I have three in that name.
不会吧 我们只订了两张
No, I don't think so, we only booked two.
然后我打电话 自己订了一张
Then I phoned back and got one for myself as well.
我是夏洛克
I'm Sherlock.
- 嗨 - 你好
- Hi. - Hello.
你就不能让我消停一晚上？
You couldn't let me have just one night off.
黄龙马戏团 在伦敦只演一夜 对上号了
Yellow Dragon Circus, in London for one day. It fits.
堂口派了一名杀手来英国
The Tong sent an assassin to England…
假扮成走钢丝的 拜托 夏洛克 正常点
Dressed as a tightrope walker. Come on, Sherlock, behave!
我们的凶手会飞檐走壁和攀绳
We're looking for a killer who can climb, who can shin up a rope.
此等身手还能去哪找？
Where else would you find that level of dexterity?
中国出境护照发放很严
Exit visas are scarce in China.
得有个好理由才能出国
They need a good reason to get out of that country.
我只需四处查看一下…
All I need to do is have a quick look around…
好呀 你去查吧 我带莎拉去买啤酒
Fine. You do that, I'll take Sarah for a pint.
我需要你帮助
I need your help.
不巧今晚我还有些别的打算
I do have a couple of other things on my mind this evening.
什么打算？
Like what?
- 你开玩笑吧 - 什么这么重要？
- You are kidding? - What's so important?
夏洛克 我在约会呢
Sherlock, I'm in the middle of a date.
你居然拉我去抓凶手 我是来…
You're going to chase some killer while I'm trying to…
干什么？
What?
我是来和莎拉一起开心的
While I'm trying to get off with Sarah.
嘿 准备好了吗？
hey… Ready?
走吧
Yeah.
你说马戏团 这不是马戏团
You said circus. This is not a circus.
看看观众的规模
Look at the size of this crowd.
夏洛克 这是…艺术
Sherlock, this is…art.
他们白天另有工作
This is not their day job.
抱歉我忘了 这不是马戏团
Sorry, I forgot, they're not a circus,
这是国际走私黑帮
they're a gang of international smugglers.
经典的中国逃脱术
Classic Chinese escapology act.
- 嗯？- 弓弦一触即发
- Hm? - The crossbow's on a delicate string.
武士得趁它发射前逃脱
The warrior has to escape his bonds before it fires.
她刺破沙袋 沙子流出来
She splits the sandbag, the sand pours out.
渐渐地 秤砣朝碗下落
Gradually, the weight lowers into the bowl.
- 谢天谢地 - 老天爷
- Thank God. - My God!
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen.
从万里之遥月色笼罩的扬子江汀
From the distant moonlit shores of the Yangtze River,
我们全心为您呈现
we present, for your pleasure,
索命中华捕鸟蛛
the deadly Chinese bird spider.
看到没？
Did you see that?
好呀 好呀
Well, well.
找到你了
Found you.
快 快 我们走
Come on. Come on. Let's go!
我派了几辆车 会堂的人早跑光了
I sent a couple of cars. The old hall is totally deserted.
听着 我在马戏团看到了 我们见过的那个纹身
Look, I saw the mark at the circus. The tattoo that we saw.
两具尸体上 那个堂口的记号
on the two bodies, the mark of the Tong.
卢奇和凡·库参与了走私行动
Lukis and Van Coon were part of a smuggling operation.
其中一人从中国偷了件珍宝
One of them stole something in China. Something valuable.
马戏团演员是黑帮派来
The circus performers were gang members…
- 追回它的 - 追回什么？
- Sent here to get it back. - Get what back?
我们不知道
We don't know.
你们不知道？
You don't know?
福尔摩斯先生 你说的我都照办了
Mr Holmes, I've done everything you asked.
雷斯垂德似乎很看重你的高见
Lestrade, he seems to think your advice is worth something.
我下令突击搜查
I gave the order for a raid.
拜托你让我有点东西交差
Please tell me I'll have something to show for it.
除了一大笔加班费用
Other than a massive bill for overtime.
明天他们就回中国了
They'll be back in China by tomorrow.
不 不达目的他们不会走人
No, they won't leave without what they came for.
得找到他们的藏身处
We need to find a hideout.
一个据点
A rendezvous.
一定就在这条信息里
Somewhere in this message it must tell us.
好吧 我还是不打扰你们了
Well, I think perhaps I should leave you to it.
- 你不必走 留下吧 - 对 你现在走最好
- No, u don't have to go. Stay. - Yes, it'd be better if u left now.
他开玩笑的 不介意就请留下吧
He's kidding. Please stay if you'd like.
我饿坏了 你们不吗？
Is it just me or is anyone else starving?
老天啊
Oh, God.
这就是你们的工作啊
So this is what you do.
你和约翰 靠解谜过日子
You and John, you solve puzzles for a living.
是咨询侦探
Consulting detective.
这些蚯蚓文是什么？
What are these squiggles?
是数字 古老的中国异体字
They're numbers. An ancient Chinese dialect.
是啊 这种常识我居然都不懂
Oh, right. Well, of course I should have known that.
我弄了潘趣酒和一碗点心
I've done punch and a bowl of nibbles.
赫德森太太 你真是天使
Mrs Hudson, you are a saint.
要是今天周一 我就能去超市了
If it was Monday, I'd have been to the supermarket.
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you. Thank you.
- 那么这些数字是密码？- 正是
- So these numbers, it's a cipher? - Exactly.
每对数字代表一个词？
And each pair of numbers is a word?
你怎么知道？
How did you know that?
有两个词已经破译出来了 在这
Well, two words have already been translated. Here.
- 约翰 - 嗯？
- John. - Mmm?
约翰 来看这个
John, look at this.
博物馆的素琳 她开始帮我们破译了
Soo Lin at the museum, she started to translate the code for us.
我们没看见
We didn't see it.
九百
Nine mill.
是说百万吗？
Does that mean millions?
九百万镑 干什么的？
Nine million quid. For what?
我们得找到句子的结尾
We need to know the end of this sentence.
你去哪？
Where are you going?
去博物馆 修复室
To the museum, to the restoration room.
- 肯定就在我们眼皮底下 - 什么啊？
- We must have been staring right at it. - At what?
书 约翰 那本书 破译密码的钥匙
The book, John. The book. The key to cracking the cipher.
素琳拿它破译的 我们绕着展厅跑时
Soo Lin used it to do this. Whilst we were running around the gallery,
她就开始破译了 肯定还在她桌上
she started to translate the code. It must be on her desk.
出租车
Taxi!
[德语]抱歉 借过
Entschuldigen Sie, bitte.
[德语]多谢了
Ja, danke!
人人都会有的书
A book that everybody would own.
（伦敦街道图）
[德语]请等一下
Please, wait!
[德语]抱歉
Bitte!
[德语]他要干嘛？
Was wollt er?
[德语]喂 你干什么啊
Hey, du, was machst du?
- [德语]马上好 - 书还给我
- Minute! - Gib mir doch mein Buch zuruck!
对 不 显然不是
Yeah. No, absolutely.
我是说 安静在家待一晚 谨遵「医嘱」
I mean, a quiet night in is just what the doctor ordered.
我是说 一般我不介意出去逛逛
I mean, I love to go out of an evening.
和中国黑帮单挑一下
and wrestle a few Chinese gangsters generally,
- 可这也太夸张了 - 好吧
- but a girl can get too much. - OK.
叫点外卖吗？
shall we get a takeaway?
好啊
Yeah.
第15页 第1条
Page 15, entry 1…
「死人」
Dead man.
的确在威胁要杀他们
You were threatening to kill them.
这是第一个密码
That's the first cipher.
9… 0… 15…
嗯 15页第36
er, 15 and 36.
36页第39 第39…
36, 39, 39…
第39…
39…
9…
九…百万…的…
"Nine", "mill", "for"…
哎呀 真快 我下去取
Blimey, that was quick. I'll just pop down.
要我摆桌子吗？
Do you want me to lay the table?
- 摆出来吃？- 对
- Um…eat off trays? - Yeah.
70页第35…
70…35…
玉…
Jade…
抱歉久等了 多少钱？
Sorry to keep you. How much do you want?
- 在你这吗？- 什么？
- Do you have it? - What?
- 宝贝在你这吗？- 我不明白
- Do you have the treasure? - I don't understand.
九百万的玉簪
"Nine mill for Jade pin.
龙穴 黑色…
"Dragon den, black…
电车道
"tramway."
约翰 约翰 我懂了
John! John, I've got it.
密码 书 是他们的伦敦街道图…
The cipher, the book. It's the London A-Z that they're us…
「书富如入海」
A book is like a magic garden,
「百货皆有」
carried in your pocket.
- 中国谚语 福尔摩斯先生 - 我…
- Chinese proverb, Mr Holmes. - I'm…
我不是夏洛克·福尔摩斯
I'm not Sherlock Holmes.
真不好意思 光说没用
Forgive me if I do not take your word for it.
信用卡 名字是…
Debit card, name of…
夏·福尔摩斯
S Holmes.
用我的卡吧
Take my card.
对 这不是我的 是他借我的
Yes, that's not actually mine. He lent that to me.
一张5000镑支票 开给夏洛克·福尔摩斯先生
And a cheque for 5, 000 made out in the name of Mr Sherlock Holmes.
对 他让我保管的
Yeah, he gave me that to look after.
你从剧院领的票 购买者也是福尔摩斯
Tickets from the theatre collected by you, name of Holmes.
对 好吧
Yes, OK.
名字呢？还是福尔摩斯
What's the name? Er, Holmes.
是容易误会
I realise what this looks like.
可我不是他
But I'm not him.
- 我们听你亲口说过 - 什么？
- We heard it from your own mouth. - What?
「我是夏洛克·福尔摩斯 我总是单枪匹马」
"I am Sherlock Holmes and I always work alone."
因为谁也跟不上我出色的头脑
Because no-one else can compete with my massive intellect.
我真这么说过？
Did I really say that?
估计我说那是学他的
I suppose there's no use me trying to persuade you.
你也不信吧
I was doing an impression.
我姓单
I am Shan.
你…你就是单？
You're… You're Shan?
我们三次试图杀你和你同伴 福尔摩斯先生
Three times we tried to kill you and your companion, Mr Holmes.
一个杀手杀人都不利落 说明什么？
What does it tell you when an assassin cannot shoot straight?
说明他们根本没想杀你
It tells you that they're not really trying.
电车道
Tramway.
- 这次不是空包弹了 - 好吧
- Not blank bullets now. - OK.
若我们想杀你 福尔摩斯先生 你已经死了
If we wanted to kill you, Mr Holmes, we would have done it by now.
我们只是想引蛇出洞
We just wanted to make you inquisitive.
- 在你那吗？- 什么东西？
- Do you have it? - Do I have what?
- 宝贝 - 我不懂你们说的
- The treasure. - I don't know what you're talking about.
这我可得验一验
I would prefer to make certain.
她的命也有价码 信息
And the price for her life, information.
- 簪子在哪？- 什么？
- Where's the hairpin? - What?
皇后的簪子 值900万镑的
The Empress pin valued at 900 million sterling?
我们已经找到买主了
We already had a buyer in the West.
我们一个人见财起意 私吞了它
and then one of our people was greedy, he took it,
带回了伦敦 而你 福尔摩斯先生 一直在找
brought it back to London, and you, Mr Holmes, have been searching.
求你 求你听我说 我不是…
Please, please. Listen to me. I'm not…
我不是夏洛克·福尔摩斯 你一定要相信
I'm not Sherlock Holmes. You have to believe me.
我没找到你们要的东西
I haven't found whatever it is you're looking for.
- 我想请一位观众来参与 - 不要 求求你
- I need a volunteer from the audience. - No, please, please!
啊 谢谢 女士
Ah, thank you, lady.
对 你非常合适
Yes, you'll do very nicely.
女士们先生们 万里之遥月色笼罩的伦敦西一区
Ladies and gentlemen, from the distant, moonlit shores of NW1,
我们全心为您献上
we present for your pleasure,
- 夏洛克·福尔摩斯的伙伴死里逃生 - 求你
- Sherlock Holmes' pretty companion in a death-defying act. - Please!
你都看过演出了 一定觉得无聊吧
You've seen the act before. How dull for you.
提前知道结果了
You know how it ends.
我不是夏洛克·福尔摩斯
I'm not Sherlock Holmes!
我不相信你
I don't believe you.
你应该信的
You should, you know.
夏洛克·福尔摩斯和他截然不同
Sherlock Holmes is nothing at all like him.
你会怎么描述我 约翰？
How would you describe me, John?
- 机智 活力 神秘？- 迟到？
- Resourceful? Dynamic? Enigmatic? - Late?
枪是半自动的 一旦发射
That's a semi-automatic. If you fire it,
子弹会以每秒千米的速度射出
the bullet will travel at over 1, 000 metres per second.
所以呢？
Well?
所以
Well…
这条隧道半径将近四米
…the radius curvature of these walls is nearly four metres.
走火了 子弹会反弹
If you miss, the bullet will ricochet.
谁都可能中弹
Could hit anyone.
还可能弹回墙壁 打中你自己
Might even bounce off the tunnel and hit you.
没事了
It's all right.
你没事了 全结束了
You're going to be all right. It's over now.
别害怕
Don't worry.
下次约会不会这样了
Next date won't be like this.
我们先撤了 不必在报告里提我们
We'll just slip off. No need to mention us in your report.
- 福尔摩斯先生 - 我很看好你 探长
- Mr Holmes… - I have high hopes for you, Inspector.
你前途光明
A glittering career.
你我唯首是瞻
I go where you point me.
正是
Exactly.
这么说 九百万 百万
So, nine million. Million.
百万 对 「九百万的玉簪 龙穴 黑色电车道」
Million, yes. Nine million for Jade pin dragon den black tramway.
给全伦敦同伙的指示
An instruction to all their London operatives.
一条信息 他们在找的东西
A message. What they were trying to reclaim.
- 什么 一支玉簪？- 值九百万
- What, a jade pin? - Worth nine million.
带去电车道 他们的伦敦据点
Bring it to the Tramway, their London hideout.
等等 一支玉簪值九百万？
Hang on. A hairpin worth nine million?
- 显然是 - 怎么这么贵？
- Apparently. - Why so much?
这取决于谁戴过
Depends who owned it.
两个伦敦分舵的成员
Two operatives based in London.
他们去大连走私花瓶
They travel over to Dalian to smuggle those vases.
其中一个藏了点私 一支小玉簪
One of them helps himself to something, a little hairpin.
- 值九百万镑 - 艾迪·凡·库干的
- Worth nine million. - Eddie Van Coon was the thief,
他在中国时偷的宝贝
he stole the treasure when he was in China.
你怎么知道是凡·库 不是卢奇？
How do you know it was Van Coon, not Lukis?
- 连杀手都不知道 - 因为皂液
- Even the killer didn't know that. - Because of the soap.
- 我是阿曼达 - 他给你带了件礼物
- Amanda? - He brought you a present.
哦 你好
Oh, hello.
从中国带回来的小礼物
A little gift when he came back from China.
- 你怎么知道？- 你不止是他的助理吧
- How do you know that? - You weren't just his PA, were you?
有人嚼舌根了吧
Someone's been gossiping.
- 没有 - 那我就不明白…
- No. - Then I don't understand why…
他家里的洗手香皂液
Scented hand soap in his apartment.
300毫升装 快见底了
300ml of it. Bottle almost finished.
- 怎样？- 我不觉得艾迪·凡·库像
- Sorry…? - I don't think Eddie Van Co.
是会买洗手液的男人
was the type of chap to buy himself hand soap,
除非他常有女客上门
not unless he had a lady coming over.
而且和你桌上的护手霜一个牌子
And it's the same brand as that hand cream there on your desk.
听着 我们不是认真的
Look, it wasn't serious between us.
露水姻缘罢了 不可能长久 他是我老板
It was over in a flash, it couldn't last. He was my boss.
怎么回事 你为什么要分手？
What happened? Why did you end it?
我觉得他不珍惜我
I thought he didn't appreciate me.
对我毫不在乎
Took me for granted.
总是放我鸽子
Stood me up once too often.
说好一起度周末的 他突然就走了
We'd plan to go away for the weekend, and then he'd just leave.
打个招呼就飞去中国了
Fly off to China at a moment's notice.
然后从国外带了礼物向你道歉
And he brought you a present from abroad to say sorry.
我能看看吗
Can I just have a look at it?
（两万英镑）
他真的爬上了阳台？
He really climbed up onto the balcony?
窗户上钉个木条 你就高枕无忧了
Nail a plank across the window and all your problems are over.
谢谢
Thanks.
他说在街头市场买的
He said he bought it in a street market.
我可不相信 我觉得他是偷的
Oh, I don't think that's true. I think he pinched it.
对 艾迪做得出来
Yeah, that's Eddie.
也不知道它值钱 只觉得适合你
Didn't know its value, just thought it would suit you.
哦 值多少钱？
Oh? What's it worth?
九百万
Nine million.
我的天啊
Oh, my God.
Oh, my God!
九百万
Nine million?!
一千年前的文物
Over 1, 000 years old.
天天放在她床头
and it's sitting on her bedside table every night.
他不知道它的价值 不知道为何被追杀
He didn't know its value. Didn't know why they were chasing him.
早知如此 该买个招财猫给她
Should've just got her a lucky cat.
- 你很介意 对吧 - 什么？
- You mind, don't you? - What?
单帮主 让她逃了
That she escaped. General Shan.
抓住了她两个打手并不够
It's not enough that we got her two henchmen.
肯定是个庞大的组织 约翰
Must be a vast network, John.
几千名成员
Thousands of operatives.
你我两人 不过触及了皮毛
You and I, we barely scratched the surface.
密码你还是破译了 夏洛克
You cracked the code though, Sherlock.
也许迪莫克拿着它 能把他们一网打尽
And maybe Dimmock can track down all of them now he knows it.
不 不 我破译了这一个密码
No. No, I crack this code,
走私者只需重新选一本书
all the smugglers have to do is pick up another book.
没有你…
Without you…
没有你帮助
without your assistance,
我们不会有路子来伦敦
we would not have found passage into London.
多谢你
You have my thanks.
（莫：感激没有意义 你不过想我继续庇护罢了）
我们没料到…
We did not anticipate…
半路杀出个程咬金
We did not know this man would come.
这个夏洛克·福尔摩斯
This Sherlock Holmes.
现在你的安全受到威胁了
And now your safety is compromised.
（莫：他们追踪不到我身上）
我不会泄露你的身份的
I will not reveal your identity.
（莫：我十分肯定）